<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration against all profession and professors that have not the life of what they profess, from the righteous seed of God; whom the world, priests, and people scornfully calls Quakers, who are in that life that the holy men of God were in, and witness that power that made them to tremble and quake, and shook the earth, and threw it down; which the world, priests, people, and professors, having the words declared from this power and life, but not it, scoffs and scorns at, but this is our riches.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E809_8</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866609</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E809[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration against all profession and professors that have not the life of what they profess, from the righteous seed of God; whom the world, priests, and people scornfully calls Quakers, who are in that life that the holy men of God were in, and witness that power that made them to tremble and quake, and shook the earth, and threw it down; which the world, priests, people, and professors, having the words declared from this power and life, but not it, scoffs and scorns at, but this is our riches.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the Black spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: G.F. [i.e., George Fox].</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 28"; "3" in imprint date crossed out and replaced with ms. "4."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:167910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Againſt all PROFESSION AND PROFESSORS THAT Have not the Life of what they Profeſs, from the Righteous ſeed of God; whom the World, Prieſts, and People, ſcornfully calls QUAKERS, Who are in that Life that the holy Men of God were in, and witneſs that power that made them to Tremble and quake, and ſhook the earth, and threw it down; which the World, Prieſts, People, and Profeſſors, having the words declared from this power and life, but not it, ſcoffs and ſcorns at, but this is our Riches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread Eagle at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:167910:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:167910:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration againſt all Profeſſion and Profeſſors that have not the life of what they do Profeſſe, from the righteous ſeed of God whom the world, Prieſts and People ſcornfully cals Quakers, who are in that life that the holy men of God were in, and witneſſe that power that made them to tremble, and Quake, and Shooke the Earth and threw it downe, which the World, Prieſts, People and Profeſſors, having the words declared from this power and life but not it, ſcornes at, but this is our riches.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He word of the living God to fly abroad to the light of Chriſt in all conſciences, that with it the word may be witneſſed, and their minds may be guided up to God and kept up to Chriſt, and it loved, in which light is unity, that all that which is contrary to this light may with it be hewen down, judged down and condemned.</p>
            <p>All whoſe minds turn from this light into the earth, into the luſt, into the curſed ſpeaking, into the preſumption and rauntings; all ſuch ranters with the light which is eternall doe we judge and condemne eternally, for with the light they are condemned from God, and all their beggarly luſts, in which light we have unity, which light doth not change, and with it all ſuch Ranters and rauntings muſt be limited, bound and chained, and for judgment, and with the eternall to be brought under.</p>
            <p>And all their great ſwelling words, and all their boaſting of their communion with God and Chriſt; when their communion is with darkneſſe, and they themſelves the ſervants of corruption, with that which is pure and eternall, they are ſeen and judged, and all their Imagined libertie, which they are got into, which ariſeth out of the earthly part: by the light they are ſeen, that they have ſlaine the witneſſes which declared againſt all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and now their underſtandings are darkned, and the eye put out, and the ſavour loſt; and now they call all things one; light, and darkneſſe one; and now their glory is to commit ſin with greedineſſe: and ſaith they are redeemed into libertie: with the Inviſible eye of the Lord, they are ſeen and condemned by the light: and now their wills is at libertie, ſpeaks, acts, and thinks, and the Son of perdition is head, and now their Ayrie minds are puffed up, and dreams of a power to come, but have ſlighted the day of their viſitation, and hath turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe; and trampled under foot the blood of the Son of God, and ſo are all condemned by all the Children of the light: and all their filthie practiſes we deny: and they muſt be troden in the wine-preſſe of the wrath of God, without the Citie, as a juſt recompence of their reward, who blaſpheme and cauſes to be blaſphemed, the name of the living God; but the eternal power of the living God, which is made manifeſt in the children of light, hath ſeen and doe ſee them and judge them by that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167910:3"/>
which everlaſting, that they ſhall goe into utter darkneſſe and down into the pit with all the uncircumciſed.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that turne from the light which is eternall, and doth not change into the earth, into the luſt, and their earthly ends, who would Levell others, Levelling with their earthly nature, and ſpeaking of the things of God through the luſts of the fleſh, with the eternall light are all ſuch actions and practiſes condemned; and who goe under a colour of Levelling we deny, which are for the earth, and which is to draw peoples mindes into the earth, with the light and power which brings out of the earth, do we all them and that deny, but that which overturnes the earth, and bringeth out of it we owne, and in it we have unity, which brings into the right order all the creation, and the right uſe of all the creatures, throweh down the Mountains, and exalteth the vallies, raiſeth up the juſt and throweth down the unjuſt, but that which would have eaſe and filthineſſe, and draws from the light which is pure, which will keep all diligent to ſerve God, and to levell the filthy nature and judge it down, we deny, and them that ſtaine the earth and cumbers the ground with the eternall light which brings the mind up out of the earth into oneneſſe in the light, we judge and comprehend; and here is the croſſe of Chriſt to keep the mind out of the earth up to God, with the light of God and with the light to ſee it is the Lords, and with it to receive wiſdome from God to labour, and to order and rule in he earth, this we own, this we honour and ſet upp in our ſoules, which layes low, and throws down and condemnes and judges all filthineſſe, beaſtlyneſſe, and the liberty in the fleſh, for who, witneſſe the power of the Lord and the light of God it throwes down that nature among them whom the world ſcornfully calls Quakers; But ſuch that dwel in the light, whoſe minds are guided up to God to receive the wiſdom from God, to labor in the Creation, whoſe minds are kept out of the earth, above the earth, up to God, and are come into the wiſdom of God, to labour with a ſingle eye, and with a ſingle heart, to ſerve one another in love, ſuch Levellers that levels down the corruption and the filth, with us are honoured.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which have been enlightened with the light of Chriſt, and not knowing nor abiding in the daily croſs of Chriſt, which crucifies the world, and the luſts, and brings to wait on Chriſt for power and ſtrength, to cleanſe the mind, to purifie the heart, and to witneſſe the life of Chriſt, have gotten the truth in motion, and in their vain minds ſtudy to comprehend the truth, and boaſt of words, but do not abide in the doctrine of Chriſt, to be comprehended into the truth, and to p ſſeſſe the life and ſubſtance, but have their wils at liberty, ſporting themſelves, in the day time, talking of a Virgin ſtate, and ſeparating themſelves, man from the wiſe outwardly, but living in riot and exceſſe, in laughter and folly, in pride and luſt, no ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being made in the heart the precious from the vile, the clean from the unclean, nor walking in the ſteps of Chriſt, but talk of high
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167910:3"/>
things in their ayrie imaginations, without life, without power, without ſavour, promiſing liberty to others, but they themſelves ſerving the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the Eye, and the pride of life, all ſuch virgins which are harlots, and their virgin ſtate with the light of Chriſt &amp; the life, which brings out of the luſts out of the earth and redeems to God, and makes pure the heart from all the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of women, and to follow the Lamb to the Virgin ſtate whoſe garments are waſhed in the blood of the Lamb, where nothing that is not pure can enter, are they ſeen and comprehended, and their eſtate known to be in the fleſh, and with the life which is eternal, which is not of this world nor in this world, which is raiſed up through death to the world, and all things of the world are they judged, and with the light which comes from Chriſt, which leads to the life inviſible, eternall, out of all viſible and carnal things are they condemned.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the light of Ieſus Chriſt within, and follows their own ſpirits and conceivings, and imaginations, and what they ſtudy in their own brain of thoſe words that were from the light declared with the light, all ſuch are comprehended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, their race and their compaſſe is known and ſeen with the light, and all ſuch we do deny, and in the light we have unity which doth them condemne.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the light which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightned withall, whoſe minds are in books, and ſo boaſts in their talke of others words which were declared, from the light and ſpeak high and bigg ſwelling words, and has mens perſons in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, all ſuch we do deny with the light of Chriſt Ieſus, which with it they are all to be condemned, which light is according to that of God in all Conſciences, and to it are we manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which do obſerve the commands which Chriſt hath ſpoken, the Prophets have ſpoken, and the Apoſtles ſpoke, and are not led with the light which comes from Chriſt, with the light are they and all their taken on commands condemned, which are taken on in that nature contrary to the light, as the Iewes and the Phariſes did, and ſuch that cry up the Ordinances of God, the Ordinances of Chriſt, the Temple of the Lord, the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of the word; and are not led to know theſe things with the light which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightened withall in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, with this light wherewith he hath enlightened every one that come into the world, all they are to be condemned and all their Ordinances and commands, and are ſuch as uſe their tongues, which acts in the nature contrary to the light, and are not led with an eternall principle of life, to know thoſe words, which were given from the life, ſo with it they are judged, and the light with it they are condemned; but all ſuch who are are led with the light, and walk in the light, into the Ordinances of Chriſt, his commands, and with the light come to witneſſe the word and the Goſpel, ſuch we own ſuch we witneſs and honour in our ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:167910:4"/>And all ſuch which turne from the light of Chriſt, which is given to every one to lead up to Chriſt them that wait in it, and direct to Chriſt them that in it ſeek to find him and, pretend to be ſeekers and waiters, and meet together, and there talke of ſeeking and waiting, but have not their minds turned to the light, nor that eye opened which ſees Chriſt which is the light, which is within, but ſeeks without, and looks without, ſeeking the living among the dead, looking for things without, and a day and power to come hereafter, but neglect the day of their viſitation which is to day, and not waiting in the light, but talking from their vain wiſdome of waiting on Chriſt, with the light which comes from Chriſt, which ſhuts out the wiſdome and the reaſon of man, and puts a ſtop to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward will, and ſtops the running mind, and brings to ſtand ſtill in the light, and to wait on Chriſt, whoſe kingdom is within and comes with obſervation, who is the ſubſtance and the life of all figures and ſhadowes, are they all ſeen and condemned.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the light which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightened withall, and are in their carnall mind, and the carnall mind imitates croſſes, and formes croſſes and Images, and worſhips the name of the Saints, with the light which is a croſſe to the ground of theſe croſſes; is he the founder of theſe Images and his Images to be condemned, and the croſſe is to the ground of all theſe croſſes, which is his condemnation and all his workes, he that hath the eare let him hear, and the eye which is the light let him ſtand ſtill and looke and ſee that which God is confounding, dwelling in the light is a croſſe to the ground of all the worlds croſſes, Papiſts Ranters, Levellers, and all who are in Notions, whoſe minds are turned from the light of Chriſt Ieſus into the earth, ſuch are enemies to the croſſe and with the light they are all condemned, and in this croſſe do we rejoyce which takes away the foundation of the world, for the Lamb of God is ſlain while it is ſtanding, ſo the croſſe is to that, that which ſhall change and doth change and paſſe away and have an end, with that which ſhall have no end, he that can receive me let him, it that I have unity, and that is it which reads all words that are declared from the life.</p>
            <p>And all who makes a profeſſion of Chriſt and God, and are drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and are covetous and Idolaters, and adulterers, whore-mongers, with the light which lets ſee all theſe things to be contrary to God, with it we do them and their profeſſion deny, for in the light is our vnity which brings to deny all deeds of darkneſſe, which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of all who lives in the fleſh, and follows the luſts of it I ſpeak; and it I witneſſe which ſhall condemn all ſuch practiſes.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the light of Ieſus Chriſt within, and makes a profeſſion of the words proceeded from the light in others, and of Chriſts words the light and the Apoſtles who were witneſſes of the light and had this light in them, and have gotten their words to talke of, and followes Bowls, and Cards, and Dice,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:167910:4"/>
and Shovelboard, and Tables, and delighting in Muſick, Harps, and Viols, which are acted in the firſt nature, Bearebaitings, Horſe-racings, Cudgell plays, Foot-ball plays, Leapings, Dancings, Wreſtlings, Fencings, all ſuch practiſes, boaſters, which are ſuch Ranters we deny, as knowing with the light all this to be condemned, and all profeſſors which profeſſe God and Chriſt and act ſuch things we deny, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be the works of the fleſh, which are to be condemned with the light.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that follows Hawking, Hunting, Cock-fightings, Stage-plays, and all other plays whatſoever, Tennis, Shooting, and other exerciſes to recreat the vain carnall mind which is out of the feare of God, and lives in the luſt of the fleſh, and the luſts of the eye, and yet makes a profeſſion, and all ſuch we deny who live in the light of Ieſus Chriſt, and with it we ſee all theſe works of the fleſh and luſt, and vainly are to be condemned with it.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that makes a profeſſion of Chriſt Ieſus, and are deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their trading, in their buyings and ſellings, in their merchandize, which are more then yea, and nay, and are in oathes, all ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors ſtink before the Lord God, and with the light which comes from Chriſt which brings to yea and nay, we all ſuch deny, for in it is our unity, which brings to pure comunication, and to the holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, then words are ſavoury and ſeaſoned with grace, and all ſuch filthie practiſes we know, are with the light to be condemned.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch teachers which are turned from the light of Ieſus Chriſt, and keeps their people from it, and ſo tells people of a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate call, mediate meanes, that the ſteeple-houſe is the Church, Hebrew, Greek and Latine is the Originall, which Pilate had, and the naturall man may have the words declared from the life into the naturall language yet never know the Originall, yet never knew the Original from whence they come, and <hi>Mathew Marke Luke</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> is the Goſpel, and ſprinkling Infants is the baptiſme, and bread and wine is the communion, ſuch draws forth the immediate to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, and tell them its the means, ſo with the immediate are all ſuch judged, and the everlaſting Goſpel witneſſed, and the comunion knowne in the ſpirit, and the baptiſme in the ſpirit, and the Church in God, and the immediate call, but all the mediate we deny, with the imediate, and ſee them to be carnall beggarly worldly rudiments and wither, and to be condemned with the light which ſhall never wither.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch teachers which are turned from the light of Ieſus Chriſt we deny, which ſeek for their gaine from their quarter, bear rule by their means, are hirelings, and ſeeks for the fleece, and makes a prey upon the people, and ſue them at the law, and are called of men Maſter, have the chiefeſt place in the aſſemblies, and ſtand praying in the Synagogues, and takes guifts and rewards, the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and are erred from the ſpirit, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was, with the ſpirit all ſuch we deny, who are in the way of Core, gainſaies the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167910:5"/>
truth, and in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> turned from the pure command, and are in envy with the light which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightened withall, we ſee ſuch as the Prophets ſaw, Chriſt ſaw, and the Apoſtles ſaw, ſo with the ſame light as they ſaw withall, we do ſee that which they teſtified againſt, and that which they denyed we deny, for in it we have unity, and all them we deny (praiſed be God) which we ſee are for condemnation with the light.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from this pure light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened withall, and makes a profeſsion of Chriſt, of God, &amp; lives in the luſt, their minds turned into the earth, in the faſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of the world, adorning themſelves with gold, plattings of the Haire, Broydered hoods and Uailes, and round attire like the moone, which can ſcarce tell how to walk upon the earth, envying one another, and ſerving luſts and pleaſures, ſporting themſelves, feaſting and rioting and profeſſing liberty to all theſe things, in all theſe things, theſe are ſuch that the Apoſtle ſpoke of, who while they profeſſe themſelves liberty are the ſervants of corruption, and all ſuch prrfeſſion, and all ſuch liberty we do deny, for with the light we do it ſee, and that liberty muſt be limited and condemned, for ſuch are they that crucifie the Son of God, which who are made free, are made free by the Son of God, from the bondage of corruption, then the creature ſhall not groan, which while the bondage of Corruption the Creation groans; who are ſervants of Corruption, turn from the light, and with the light they are to be condemned, and all that liberty, ſo all ſuch profeſſors and profeſſion, and ſuch liberty we do deny.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that are turned from the pure light of Ieſus Chriſt which is eternall, and have got a fained love, a fained profeſſion, a fained humility, and a cuſtomary falſe ſighing and falſe groaning, all ſuch with the light we do deny, as ſeeing they are for condemnation but true humility, true love, and ſighing and groaning we own, which is in it ſelfe, its ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that are turned from the pure light which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightened withall, and makes a profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and his words, and ſues one another at the law, and ſtrive about the earthly things, and wrangle about earthly things, and ſtrive about things that are changeable, and vexing and fretting one another about ſuch things in Courts, Aſſizes, and Benches and Suites, here you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare where your minds are, and what they are upon, and to, and here you declare that you are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, and are they that are turned from the light and all ſuch filthy profeſſion and profeſſors, we utterly deny with the light, which is your condemnation.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch teachers and people that are turned from the pure light of Chriſt within them, and turnes the words that were declared from the light into Rime and meeter, propheſies, Prayers, Cryings, Tremblings, makes ſongs of them to ſtir up the carnal mind, ſome part they ſing, ſome part they take and make a prayer of, that part they turne into Rime and Meeter and ſing then they doff their Hats, which when they read they keep them on;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:167910:5"/>
here they worſhip the work of their own hands, another part of the ſame mind goes to expound and get mony withall, all ſuch as thus abuſe the Scripture with their carnall minds, and makes them bend to their own fancies we do utterly deny, for the ſpirit we witneſſe that gave forth the Scriptures, and we own the words again, and they are ours, and all ſuch prayers, and all ſuch ſingers, and all ſuch preachers and expounders, with that nature that acts contrary to the light, with the light all ſuch are to be condemned, with the light we ſee that condemnation is upon all ſuch, in which light we have unity which gathers our hearts together to God, which brings us to witneſſe praying, to witneſſe ſinging in the ſpirit, which ſpirit opens the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures without any private interpretation.</p>
            <p>And all ye that are in warrs are turned from the light, from whence riſe wars but from the luſt, which with the light all wars and that warring nature is to be condemned, for it will lead before warrs was, into another kingdom which is not of this world, that which is turned from the ſight, warres for the kingdomes of the world, but he that is guided with the light, comes to warr againſt the kingdoms of the world, and with it comes to be led before warres was, and to you this is the word of the living God, he that can receive it let him.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the pure eternall light, which Ieſus Chriſt hath enlightened withall, and are in ſtrife about earthly things and Cuſtomes, and Lawes, and Acts, and one Nations Cuſtome would bring another nation to bend to his Nations Cuſtome, and one man to have his fancie to reigne over another mans fancie, &amp; one mans opinion over another mans opinion, here you are making profelites with the nature out of the truth; And thou that doſt reign to gather all nations under thee, and have all bow to thy image, remember <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of the many languages of the many Nations, he loſt his kingdom; with the light which comes from Chriſt which is eternall, which brings out of all Languages into one Language, all this is to be condemned and judged down, which light brings to witneſſe another King, Chriſt Ieſus, whoſe kingdome and dominion endures for ever, who daſhes to pieces all thoſe dead ſtones, and gathers together the living ſtones, who doth redeeme out of Languages, out of People, out of tongues, out of kindreds, makes Prieſts and Kings to reigne upon the earth, praiſed be God, Chriſt Ieſus is, come to reign; and coming to reign, and with this light which lets ſee all theſe thing conscrary to the light, Cuſtomes, Traditions, Opinions who live in, and yet make a profeſſion of God and Chriſt, and profeſſe liberty, and are delivered to act all ſuch things, are in the nature contracted to God, and with the light them and all thoſe things we do deny.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that turne from the light of Chriſt Ieſus and lives in the earthly wiſdome, and would have others bow down to them, and would have the earth honored, and the earthly honored, and yet profeſſe Chriſt and God, and are in the evill communication and teacheth it; that you muſt not ſay yea at firſt word, but nay and then take a thing,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:167910:6"/>
that's manners; here you are in the evill and your manners, are corrupt and all your manners I deny, for evill communication doth corrupt the good manners, and thou that art more in thy communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then yea and nay, thou art in the evill thou art not in the good manners, but in the evill comunication corrupted, o with the light thou art to be condemned, thy communication and thy manners, and thy profeſſion to be deceipt, and a lying tongue is found in thee, which is abhored with God.</p>
            <p>And all ye Merchants who have great traffique by Sea and Land, and all ye which do change the creatures, which are above yea and nay, if ye make a profeſſion of Chriſt. we deny you, your manners is corrupt and you and your profeſſion is to be condemned out of the doctrine of Chriſt, therefore ſilence all fleſh, before the Lord God, who makes a profeſſion of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt his words, and Apoſtles words, and Prophets words and are contrary to his doctrine, with his light you are to be condemned from him to it in you all, I ſpeak which lets you ſee your communication and converſation; for being yea and nay in your communication here you are all kept in the good manners, you are all trained up to and in the holy converſation which is without ſpot, and the converſation muſt be in heaven, and the converſation is in Heaven who comes to walk here.</p>
            <p>And to all you which are turned from the light, the word of the Lord, I do charge you &amp; command you in the preſence of the living God, yee Merchants yee Traffiquers, yee Shopkeepers, yee Tradesmen of all ſorts whatſoever, to the light of Chriſt Ieſus in all your conſciences, wherewith he hath enlightened you take heed, and it love and mind, that with it you may ſee in all your common occaſions when you are more then yea, and nay, ye goe into the evill, ye goe into your ſelf ends, yea goe into the corrupt manners, yee goe into the filthy communications, and the wicked converſation, and lay aſide all guile and deceit, and ſpeak not that of your commodities which they are not, to diſſemble, to lye, and to cheat and deceive the ſimple to get gaine to your ſelves, but make your price reaſonable and be at a word to the poore and to the rich, to the wiſe and the ſimple, and what the word is let it ſtand, let your yea be yea, leaſt a lye be found in your mouthes, and let all your Trade and Trafique and Merchandize be for thoſe things that are uſefull and ſervicable in the creation and not to feed the luſts, or delight the vain mind, that ye may not burthen the Creation but may be ſerviceable in your genereation and not to feed, he that walks otherwiſe, and makes a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofeſſion of God and Chriſt his Religion is viane, and his profeſſion is abomination to the Lord, and with the light he is condemned from amongſt all the children of the light, you that profeſſe what you are not yee, are Hyprocrites, and have not the life that gave forth the Scriptures, therefore with it you are judged; Awake awake all people and come unto the light wherewith Chriſt Ieſus hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you, that with it you may ſee what you do profeſſe, and I charge
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:167910:6"/>
you and command you in the preſence of the living God to profeſſe no more then you doe profeſſe and walk in.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch who are turned from the pure light of Chriſt into vain jangling, vaine contention and ſtrife about thoſe words that were declared from the light and life; and jangling about thoſe words that were declared from the life and light, with the life and light are all ſuch judged and condemned, and thoſe words ſeen plainly that from it were given forth, and all ſuch that would goe about to make ſences of thoſe words, that were given forth from the light and life, with the light that leads out of ſence up to God, from whence words did proceed all, they and their ſences are condemned with the light, and their profeſſion in that nature that acts contrary to the light.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that are turned from the light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened withal, and doe reſpect perſons, ſuch are out of the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and profeſſe dominion and dignity, and reſpect perſons, ſuch caſt the law of God behind their backs, which reſpects no mans perſons, ſuch would have flattering titles, and give flattering titles to man, ſuch are not reſpected with the maker the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and ſuch doe not reſpect him, as it is written in Iob.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that make a profeſſion and live in that nature, its openly ſeen they are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, but the law we own, which is perfect according to that of God in all conſciences, which reſpects no mans perſon, and the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt we own which is without reſpect of Perſons.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which are turned from the light of Chriſt and makes a profeſſion of his words, and lives in bending and bowing one to another, and in it taking Pride Cap and Knee, and he that doth not deny the light, and worſhip with them in that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſuch are hated and envied, and ſcorned and ſcoffed at, now with the light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened withall, which brings us to deny all the worſhips of the world, which brings us to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in ſpirit and in truth with it all ſuch reſpects and ſuch profeſſion are condemned. And all ſuch which turns from the light of Chriſt Ieſus within and hears it not but lives in hardneſs of heart, and Oppreſſion and Pride, and Ambition gathering the earth together and makes themſelves Lords over the creatures, and oppreſſe with great fines and rents, and live in fulneſs Dives like and feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo fat they can hardly goe, and with their cloathes they dreſſe themſelves, that they can hardly tell how to walk, when the other ſcarce have Bread or Clothes, and yet they make a profeſſion of Chriſt Ieſus, and ſay that they exalt him, here the devil is exalted the King of Pride and Oppreſſion, and the lying tongue is found in their mouths. And ſuch men gets the earth under their hands, in whom the devourer rules, and the curſe is upon it, and keep it under their hands from the people from dreſſing of it, and it doth not yeild her encreaſ; &amp; none who are here waits for the Reſtoration of the Creation, but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:167910:7"/>
ſome Creatures are loſt for want of the Creatures, and ſome creatures are deſtroyed for want of ordering, where this wiſdome reignes and rules in the earthly, which is earthly, ſenſuall and diveliſh, in the nature which acts contrary to the light, with the light are all ſuch profeſſors to be condemned, and with it they are ſeen, they have not the life that gave forth the ſcriptures; ſuch cannot witneſſe Chriſt Ieſus but by hear ſay, ſuch ſwels in the vanity, ſuch ſwels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poor, ſuch ſwells againſt the needy, and the contrite heart, ſuch deſpiſes them who walk in the fear of God, and are growing into the life that gave forth the Scriptures, ſuch profeſſors and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion we deny, they have long cumbred the ground, ſuch are harlotted from the truth, and ſuch gets the earth under their hands, Commons, Waſtes and Forreſt, and Fels, and Mores, and Mountaines, and lets it lye waſt, and calls themſelves Lords of it, and keeps it from the pe ple, when ſo many are ready to ſtarve and begg; with the light that comes from Chriſt, which brings to Chriſt, all ſuch that are deſtroyers of the Creatures of the Creation, are condemned, and all earthly mindes, and all who for ſelf ends acts contrary to the light; And all whoſe minds are ſingle, and with the light guided, and receives the pure wiſdome from above, ſuch are fit to order and rule, to give the earth its liberty, that it may come to enjoy her Saboths and yield her encreaſe: But, all ſuch as make a profeſſion of the words declared from the light, and are in the ſelfiſh principle, ſuch are not fit to rule, that are in the wiſdome which is earthly, but with the light which leads into the fear of God, which is the beginning of the pure wiſdome, all that is to be condemned, by which all things comes to be ordered, and by nothing that is earthly, but with the juſt all that is judged, to the light in all your conſciences I ſpeak, that with it all your minds may be turned to God, and come to grow into the life, that gave forth the Scriptures, that every one may come to poſseſſe what you doe profeſſe, for all profeſſion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the manner of it is without the life, Opinions, Sects, they are all in that nature that acts contrary to the light, and with the light which never changeth, all ſuch we doe deny.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that turne from the light, that turne from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, turne into Cains way, and all ſuch as have had mighty openings by the ſpirit, and have erred from it and then ſuch ſet up to be teachers for guift, and rewards, and wages, all ſuch we doe deny, who goes after the error of Balaam, ſuch are they that lay ſtumbling blocks before them that dwell in their tents, ſuch are for the ſword, ſuch their fruit wither, therefore to the light in you all I ſpeak which never changeth, that with it all that may be judged with that which never changeth for all that we utterly deny.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that are turned from the light of Chriſt within, which ſay they are guifted men and experienced men, and goes forth into the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rld and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people they are guifted, and have ſo much a piece for ſpeaking their guift, here they are lyers, they have not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:167910:7"/>
received the gift of God, which cannot be bought and ſold for money, and with the light an ſuch are to be condemned which doth never change.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch as are turned from the light of Chriſt Ieſus, which have gotten words in their braine, and cals them experiences, and have had ſome flaſhes, and have ſome conceivings and let one another of theſe experiences, ſometimes with a Tobacco pipe in their mouthes taking Tobacco in the luſt and ſometime as they are drinking in in alehouſes, theſe are the evill beaſts which the ſcriptures ſpeaks of, that live in the luſts of the fleſh theſe are ſuch as defile the fleſh, and ſpeak through the luſts of the fleſh, all ſuch experiences, and ſuch meetings, and ſuch declaring of experiences, with the light and life that gave forth the ſcriptures, whoſe words were ſavoury and ſeaſoned, we utterly deny, and witneſſe the light in which we have union and fellowſhip one with another, and with God, and the Son, who teſtified againſt all the world, that the works of it were evil, and with his light we doe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch that doe not own the light, which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightned withall, to guide them, to lead them into the life, that gave forth the ſcriptures, but with that nature that hates the light, doe make the profeſſion of the ſcripture, and would be ſatisfied in things of the ſpirit and the ſcripture; that is it which muſt goe empty away; and that is he which would know, and not doe, and that is he which is approved of men, but not of God, and this is he whoſe prayers are abomination to God, with his light which comes from him are all theſe ſeen, and with it they are condemned, and all ſuch we deny, who dwels in the light which comes from God, which is eternall; the father of light.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which doe not walk in the light which comes from Ieſus Chriſt, but are turned from it, and judges for rewards, ſuch their eye is blinded which is the light, with the earth. And all ſuch that takes tithes of the people, which denies the unchangeable prieſt, and holds up the figure and brings Caeſar their cloak to hold up the figure, and yet make a profeſſion of Chriſt, oh horrible filthy, are men paſt feeling, is the ſenſible part gone, all ſuch profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors of Chriſt and God, ſuch cunning deceivers which makes words their cloak, with the light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightned us withall we deny, which brings us to witneſſe the unchangeable, with it we doe witneſſe the figure of Chriſt in its place, and with it Coeſar in his place ſhall have his due, and with it we doe witneſſe the end of the figure Chriſt Ieſus the ſubſtance. And all ſuch as hold up the figure, we doe utterly deny, as ſeeing and knowing they are to be condemned who live in thoſe changeable things, with that which doth not change, and to you this is the word of God, and the law we doe own which is according to the light of Chriſt in every mans conſcience, which law reſpects no mans perſon.</p>
            <p>And all ſuch which profeſſe themſelves Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:167910:8"/>
ſay they own Chriſt, and they do exalt him, and are in envy and perſecution, and perſecute them that declare againſt deceit, and pride, and luſt, and ſuch as the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles cried againſt, all ſuch Profeſſors and Profeſſion which is acted in that nature contrary to the light, all this is with the light to be condemned; for with the light it is to be ſeen to be out of the doctrine of Chriſt; and all you that are there in ſuch actions, you have a name that you live, but you are dead, with the life you are judged, and with the light condemned, and ſuch we deny with the light in which is the unity.</p>
            <p>And all you which do not wait to be guided by the light of Chriſt that with it your minds may be led and directed to God to ſtand in his Councell, but are making Laws and Acts and Bonds in that nature that acteth contrary to this light in the Conſcience, and then makes a profeſſion, with this nature, of thoſe words that were decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the eternall ſpirit of God, and ſo lives in theſe things that are acted contrary to the light which is eternall, now with the light which is eternall and never changeth is all this comprehended fathomed and condemned, and the Law of God witneſſed which is perfect, which endures for ever; which who walks in it, ſhall grow up as a free planted by the River of water, whoſe leaf ſhall never fade nor fall, but you that are wicked are not ſo, you are turned from the light, your fruit withers, and you are toſſed too and fro like the chaffe, for you are turned from that which is eternall to the change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the changeable things, for the Law of God ſerves all ages, which is according to that of God in every mans conſcience, which is the ſame in all ages, it endures for ever.</p>
            <p>And all you that are not led by the light of Ieſus Chriſt, which he hath enlightened you withall, which has the letter which from it was declared; which are ſuch teachers and profeſſors which ſay none ſhall have the infallible judgment, none ſhall come to have the eternall ſpirit of God as the Apoſtles had; all your profeſſion we do deny with the ſame eternall ſpirit that gave forth the ſcriptures, and with the light all ſuch are condemned, whatſoever profeſſion they are of, Sect or Opinion, that walk not in the light, and have not the life that gave forth the Scriptures, with the light they are all condemned, wherein we have unity.</p>
            <p>And all you that are turned from the light which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened you withall, though you may profeſſe the words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared from the light, and their commands which they obeyed, and yet not led by tht ſame light, with it the light you are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>And you that are turned from the light, which Chriſt Ieſus hath enlightened you withall, you are in the ſelf righteouſneſſe, you are turned from the Lord our righteouſneſſe, who are out of the light, and hate the light, and with the light you are to be condemned, and your righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:167910:8"/>From him who is a lover of your ſouls, a lover of the Seed, a lover of the Creation for the eſtabliſhing of the righteous Law, and ſetting up of righteouſneſs, and cleanſing the land of evill doers, which the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous law takes hold upon, which is perfect acccording to that of God in all conſciences, and is againſt ſuch as act contrary to the light of God in the conſcience, who is a lover of peace and unity, in that which never changeth, in that which comprehends time, in that which ſees out of time, from which love proceeds, where all the children of God in the light meet in one judgment and mind; which light is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the world; in which light they walk, where there is no ſtrife, not war for the earth, nor about the earth, but from the earth ſu h are redeemed to God the Lord, whoſe the earth is, who is come to reign, and coming to reign, Glory g ory to God Almight for ever, who liveth and reigneth and endureth forever. This is witneſſed amongſt them whom the world ſcornfully calls <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the light is ours which ſhall condemn the world, and them which do profeſs what they are not: To the light of Chriſt in you all I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee your ſelves, there is your Teacher that will not lye, which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemn you if you do lye which will witneſs me eternally, &amp; condemn you that hate it, and ſhew you all the way to ſalvacion that love it, and from Chriſt, from whence it doth come, which is the way to the Father, and to you all this is the word of God, and love and peace to your ſouls, and a viſitation.</p>
            <p>And lay aſide all your profeſſion in words, and have not the life; for you are worſe then they that make no profeſſion: for you have a cloak, you are worſe then the Publican, the open ſinner which ſees himſelf quickly, which is more juſtified, with that which lets him ſee himſelf, then you that ſtand up in your ſelf-profeſſion: with that light which comes from Chriſt, all ſelf, and all corruption and ſin is judged and condemned, and nothing is juſtified but what is ſanctified and nothing is glorified but what is juſtified, and ſo all every where r ad your ſelves, to the light in all your conſciences I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee your ſelves, where you are, what you have been, what you are, whom you ſerve, whom you worſhip, and whether you know the Father of light, or had known there had been ſuch a one, if the Scripture had not ſpoken of ſuch a one, with the light that knowledge is condemned, for its death that talks of the ſame, which knowledge is outward; and whether you had known there had been a holy Ghoſt if the Scriprure had not ſpoken of the holy Ghoſt, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you had known there had been a Chriſt, if the Scripture had not ſpoken of Chriſt: And whether you had known there had been a Goſpell if the Scripture had not ſpoken of the Goſpel, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:167910:9"/>
the light of Chriſt I ſpeak, it will let you ſee what you do poſſeſs of the life that was before the Scripture was given forth, for the word was, and the light was before the Scripture was, the chapter is not the light, nor the verſe is not the light, nor the word, but from the word, from the light and from the life were the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declared; and wi h the light, and with the word, and in the life, they are all owned again: and all that make a trade of them, with the light, and with the life, and with the word, are all ſuch denied. And all ſuch as hold up an outward Temple, their minds ate turned from the light of Chriſt within, which brings to witneſs the temple of the holy Ghoſt, and worſhips that which is turned from the light of Chriſt, which ſpeak their imaginations upon the words declared from the light, theſe are the cage of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean birds, theſe are they that do perſecute, theſe are they that paint themſelves, and ſuch are the harlots, the welfavoured harlots, and build the Tombs of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, and garniſh the ſepulchers of the righteous; but with the light which Chriſt Jeſus hath inlightned withall, which comes from him, all ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practices, and ſuch a profeſſion from God is ſeen and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, With all the children of light, who are of God, and to you all this is the word of God.</p>
            <p>This I command you all in the preſence of the living God, to walk in the light that Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightned you withall, that with it you may all come to ſee Chriſt, and walk in the light and life, as the Saints did, which from it the Scripture proceeded, and walking every one in the light and life in meaſure, you wil come to witneſs thoſe words fulfilled, that were given forth from the life, and the ſubſtance of them poſſeſs, which has been ſo long profeſt; then there will be no more, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt, Lo there is Chriſt,</hi> and toto al this is the word of God, you that of God in you al I ſpeak, that with it your minds may be ſtayed upon God, and that you may come to witneſs your ſoules quickned with the living power which raiſes it up out of death, and throws down the earth, and wait in the light which comes from Chriſt that this you may come to enjoy in life, ſubſtance and power which will lead you out of form and words, to the life that gave forth the words; for who have the words and not the life, from it are ſtrangers, and with it are to be judged, for ſo to it I ſpeak, that you may ſee what you have more then words, if you have not it with the light, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be condemned.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
